好像我应该生那个孩子的气 那个...
I feel as if I should be angry with that child, that...
天真的小姑娘 或者我不能原谅她...
naive young girl. Or that I must not forgive her...
因为她没有及时看清那个魔鬼的本质
for not recognising the nature of that monster.
因为当时她不知道自己卷入了什么
For not being aware of what she was getting into.
特别是我不加思索就同意了
And especially that I went along without thinking.
因为我不是疯狂的纳粹分子 在柏林 我本可以这么说的:
Because I wasn't a fanatical Nazi. I could have said, in Berlin:
"不 我不要去做 我不想去元首的总部"
'No, I'm not doing it. I don't want to go to the Furer's headquarters.'
但是我没有那么做 当时我太好奇了
But I didn't do that. I was too curious.
那时候我也没有意识到...
I also didn't realise...
命运把我带到了一个我完全不想去的地方
that destiny would take me somewhere I didn't want to be.
但是 我仍然很难原谅自己
But, nevertheless, I find it hard to forgive myself.
姑娘们来了
The ladies are here.
是她们 放她们过去
It's confirmed. -They can pass.
「元首总部"狼穴"」
'Wolfsschanze' headquarters of the Furer
「1942年11月 东普鲁士雷斯登堡」
November 1942 Rastenburg, East-Prussia
姑娘们 请坐
Sit down, ladies.
稍等 元首正在喂狗 过一会儿他就可以接见你们了
One moment. The Furer is feeding his dog. He'll see you in a short while.
能告诉我们... 怎样和元首打招呼吗?
Can you tell us... How are we supposed to address the Furer?
元首先给你们打招呼 然后你们只要回答 嗨 元首
The Furer first speaks to you and then you reply: Heil, mein Furer.
要行纳粹礼吗?
And the Nazi salute?
没有必要...
That won't be necessary...
因为元首要找的不是战士, 而是一个秘书
since the Furer isn't looking for a soldier, but for a secretary.
你们最好自然一些 尽可能的冷静
Act as normal and calm as you can.
我进去看看他有没有时间见你们
I'll see if he has time for you.
元首 柏林来的姑娘们到了
Mein Furer, the ladies from Berlin are here.
谢谢你们半夜跑过来
Thank you for coming in the middle of the night.
不过 在战争期间 一个人无法控制时间
Sometimes, during a war, one is not in control of time.
- 能告诉我你的名字吗?  - 玛格丽特·洛仑兹
Can I ask your name? -Margarethe Lorenz.
- 你从哪儿来的呢  - 富尔达
Where are you from? -From Fulda.
- 那么你的名字呢  - 乌苏拉·普特卡默 嗨 元首
And what is your name? -Ursula Puttkammer. Heil, mein Furer.
这个用不着 你只要告诉我 你从哪儿来
No need for that. Where are you from?
法兰克福 元首...
Frankfurt am Main, mein Fu...
汉娜·波特洛夫斯基 生于柏林 长于柏林
Hannah Potrovsky, born and raised in Berlin.
确切的说 在潘科区
In Pankow, to be precise.
海德薇希·勃朗特 来自施瓦本的克赖斯海姆
Hedwig Brandt from Crailsheim, Schwaben.
- 那么你呢  - 我叫特劳德尔·洪普斯 来自慕尼黑
And you are? -Traudl Humps. I'm from Munich.
来自慕尼黑的姑娘
A lady from Munich.
那么我们可以开始了吗? 洪普斯小姐
我的布伦蒂不会伤害你的 她非常聪明
My Blondi won't hurt you. She's very intelligent.
她比很多人还要聪明
She's much smarter than most people.
首先 请坐下来
First, sit down, please.
不要紧张 听写的时候我会出很多错的
Don't be nervous. I make many mistakes during dictation.
你不会比我错得更多的
You won't make nearly as many.
你很年轻
You're very young.
- 你多大了?  - 22 元首
How old are you? -22, mein Furer.
我的德意志同胞们...
My German fellow-countrymen and women...
... 亲爱的同志们
...fellow party members.
我想 这是很少有的...
It is, I think, rather special...
一个人在20年以后 依然可以站在他的支持者的前面...
that, after 20 years of service, a man still stands in front of his supporters...
... 而且在这20年里 他的计划从来不用调整
...and that in all those 20 years, his program never needed to be modified.
「注 非常多的错误」
我建议再来一遍
I suggest we try it again.
我成功了 他雇佣了我
I did it. He hired me.
「柏林 1945年3月20日 希特勒的56岁生日」
Berlin - 20 April 1945 Hitler's 56th birthday
「两年半后」
two and a half years later
卧倒
Take cover.
全部撤 快 快 把它从街道上搬走
Hurry. Continue. Get that off the street.
卧倒
Take cover.
是大炮的声音
That's artillery fire.
不要傻了 哪儿会有大炮呢
Don't be silly. Where would it be coming from?
你说得对 这不是空投炸弹 这就是大炮
You're right. These are no planes, this is artillery.
是俄国人 多好的生日礼物
It's the Russians. What a birthday present.
布尔格多夫 怎么回事? 哪儿来的炮声
Where is that cannon fire coming from?
生日快乐 元首
Happy Birthday, mein Furer.
柏林市中心遭到了炮轰
The city centre of Berlin is under fire.
榴弹密集轰炸勃兰登堡门和帝国国会大厦  一直到腓特烈大街火车站
Grenades have hit near the Brandenburger Tor and the Reichstag.
- 都是从哪儿来的呢  - 还不知道
Where did they come from? -We don't know yet.
- 我正在和科勒通话  - 我跟科勒说
I have Koller on the line. -Give me Koller.
科勒 你知道柏林遭到大炮攻击了吗?
Koller, do you know Berlin is under artillery fire?
- 不知道  - 你没有听到炮声吗?
No. -Can't you hear the shooting?
- 没有 我在维尔德帕克「注:柏林附近」  - 柏林乱糟糟的
No, I'm in Wildpark-Werder. -Berlin is chaotic.
俄国人应该已经占领了奥多河上的一座铁路桥
Apparently, the Russians captured a railway bridge over the Oder.
奥多河附近没有敌人的大炮
The enemy has no railway artillery near the Oder.
那不是远程大炮
It's not long-range artillery.
动物园工事附近的防空部队  报告说那是10到12厘米口径的...
The anti-aircraft defence near the Zoo-Bunker reports they're 10 to 12...
... 火炮 俄国人的大炮在马灿地区附近
... cm calibres. The Russians have positions near Marzahn.
离市中心只有12公里 俄国人已经这么近啦
That's only 12 kilometres from the centre. Are the Russians that close?
应该把德国空军的领导层统统绞死
They should hang the entire Luftwaffe leadership.
真是前所未闻
This is unheard-of.
俄国人离市中心只有12公里
The Russians are at 12 kilometres from the city centre.
没有人告诉我 要我自己问
Nobody told me anything. I had to ask.
也许真的只是远程大炮
Maybe it's long-range artillery, after all.
- 你刚才说到奥多河上的铁路桥...  - 胡说
That railway bridge over the Oder... -Nonsense.
那个希姆莱 真是个华而不实的小丑
That Himmler, such a pompous buffoon.
官僚 到处都是官僚 看着就让人难受
Party bosses, everywhere. They make me so sick.
元首今天开始"克劳塞维茨"战略
The Furer starts 'Clausewitz' today.
柏林成了前线 他守不住的 柏林完了
Berlin as a front city. He won't be able to keep the city.
如果元首呆在这儿 帝国将和他一起毁灭
If the Furer stays here, the Reich will go down with him.
我们一定要让他离开这儿 和希维尔谈谈 元首喜欢他
We have to talk him out of it. Talk to Hewel.
外交家里只有他还能对他有影响
He's the only diplomat with any influence on him.
希维尔什么办法都用过了 信我吧 没有用的
Hewel tried everything. It's useless.
那么与你妻子的姐姐谈谈
Talk to your sister-in-law, then.
为什么不呢  你太太是爱娃·布劳恩的妹妹 她也算是他的亲戚
Why not? You're married to the sister of Eva Braun.
我们什么都要试试 柏林已经被俄国人包围了
We must try everything. Berlin is almost surrounded.
你还年轻 你马上要做爸爸了
You're still young. You'll be a father soon.
- 你想死在这儿吗?  - 当然不想
Do you want to die here? -Absolutely not.
先生们 元首到
Gentlemen, the Furer.
全都扔了 不过要有点尊严 我们两个小时后离开
Everything out. Quickly. We're leaving in two hours.
- 这里怎么了?  - 打包 逃走
What's going on? -We're leaving.
"克劳塞维茨"战略已经开始了
'Clausewitz' has started.
所有的政府部门和军事部门都要撤离柏林了
All the ministries and departments are leaving Berlin.
大家都走的话 谁来照看这儿的平民和士兵呢
And who's going to look after the people and the soldiers?
- 教授 不要问我  - 这太荒唐了
Don't ask me, professor. -This is insane.
教授
Professor.
我不同意撤离我的办公室
I won't allow the evacuation of my office.
- 是吗? 你不同意?  - 柏林的食物供应将会中断
Is that so? -Food supply would collapse.
优秀的士兵总能找到食物的
A good soldier can always find food.
当战斗在整个城市爆发的时 他们去哪找? 还有平民
And when there's fighting all over the city, where does he get it? The population.
- 那是不负责任的  - 这是元首的命令
It's irresponsible. -It's an order from the Furer.
作为政府部门主管 我要向党卫军和希姆莱负责
As department head, I report to the SS and to Himmler.
但是作为一名医生 我是国防军的一员而他们还没有撤退
But as a doctor, I'm part of the Wehrmacht and they're not leaving yet.
紧记这一点
Keep that in mind.
教授可以留在柏林 给他相应的文件
The professor stays in Berlin. Get him the proper papers.
上车
We're leaving.
一切为了德意志 嗨 元首
Everything for Germany. Heil, mein Furer.
元首 我... 嗨 元首
Furer, I... Heil, mein Furer.
他们这么急着逃离这儿
They're in such a hurry to get away from here.
我最烦的是他们的马屁
The brown nosing is the worst.
他们表面说"胜利万岁"  其实背地里想的是"舔我的...你知道那个的"
They say 'Sieg Heil'. but they think 'Lick my... you know what.'
元首 我请求你 离开柏林 现在还不太晚
Mein Furer, I beg you: Leave Berlin. It is not too late yet.
太晚了吗?
Too late?
希维尔 过来一下
Hewel, come here for a moment.
我确定你也同意 我们应该和盟军联系一下...
I'm sure you agree we should contact the Allies...
- 应该采取些政治措施了  - 确实如此 我们需要采取政治措施
...and start conducting politics. -Certainly. We need politics.
政治? 我再也不搞政治了
Politics? I don't do politics anymore.
政治让我讨厌
I'm fed up with it.
等我死了 你们有足够的时间搞政治的
When I'm dead, you'll have plenty of time for politics.
- 元首...  - 很好 亲爱的希姆莱 我忠诚的海因里希
It's good, dear Himmler. My loyal Heinrich.
很好 去吧
It's good. Just go.
老实说 这个人完了
He has no strength left.
能指望素食禁酒主义者做什么呢
What did you expect from a vegetarian teetotaller?
但是 说真的 费格莱因 我必须自己去做
Seriously, though, Fegelein. I'm taking control now.
柏林几天后就要陷落
Berlin will fall in a couple of days.
元首一死 你以为盟军会和谁谈判呢
When the Furer's dead, who will the Allies negotiate with?
你凭什么认为他们要跟你谈判呢
Why do you think they'll negotiate with you?
西方需要纳粹国和我的党卫军来维持秩序
The Nazi state and my SS are needed to maintain order.
和艾森豪威尔谈上一小时 他也会这么认为的
One hour with Eisenhower and he'll feel the same way.
- 已经做了初步的接触  - 当心 这是叛国
The first contact has been made. -Careful, that's high treason.
费格莱因 我担心的是别的事
Fegelein, I have other concerns.
见了艾森豪威尔我是该行纳粹礼还是该和他握手呢
Should I give Eisenhower the Nazi salute or shake his hand?
看
Look at that.
最好的客人总是来得最晚
The best guests always arrive late.
你们已经要走了吗? 先生们 其实我还想和你谈谈
Leaving already, gentlemen? I wanted to talk to you.
- 元首的那个销毁一切的命令...  - 很遗憾 我得走了
The scorched-earth order... -I really have to go now.
改天来霍恩里岑看我吧
Come and see me one day in Hohenlychen.
不管怎样 我现在要带我的队伍去帝国北部  从那里声援柏林的战斗
I'm going north to help with the battle of Berlin there.
所以 施佩尔 我们城市上空的轰炸也有好处
You know, Speer... There's an advantage to those bombings.
清除残骸要比亲自毁掉一切更容易
It's easier to clean up debris than to demolish everything ourselves.
战争胜利以后 重建的速度将会很快
When the war will be over, reconstruction will be quick.
在这些模型上我们一起花了几千个小时
We spent thousands of hours together with these replicas.
你真是个天才 施佩尔
You're a true genius, Speer.
是的 毫无疑问 只有你我 知道不可思议...
Yes, absolutely. Only you and I know that the Third Reich would be inconceivable...
... 第三帝国只有仓库和工厂 只有摩天大楼和旅馆
...with only warehouses and factories. Skyscrapers and hotels.
第三帝国将是个持续千年的...
This Third Reich will be a treasury full of art and culture...
... 到处是文化艺术珍品的宝库
...that will survive thousands of years.
我们将看到雅典卫城...
We see, before us, the ancient cities, the Acropolis...
看到中世纪的城市... 大教堂...
We see the medieval cities... the cathedrals...
... 我们知道人们需要这个 一个中心
...and we know that the people need that.
是的 施佩尔
Indeed, Speer.
那是我过去的想像...
That was my vision...
... 现在依然是
...and it still is.
元首 如果要实现这些计划 你现在必须离开柏林
Mein Furer, if you want to realize these plans, you must leave Berlin.
爱娃 你说说看
Eva, you say something.
他是元首 他知道怎么做最好
He's the Furer. He knows what's best.
你必须离开柏林 每个人都这么说  俄国人几乎把我们包围了
You must leave Berlin. The Russians almost have us isolated.
我不能那样 孩子
I can't do that, my child.
否则我会成为一个转经轮上空无一文的喇嘛的
I would be like a lama priest with an empty prayer wheel.
我必须解决问题或者灭亡 但必须在柏林
I have to solve the problem, here in Berlin, or perish.
施佩尔...
Speer...
... 你怎么想呢?
...what do you think?
落幕的时候你必须站在舞台上
You have to be on the stage when the curtain falls.
再装
Reload.
走开 别管我
Go away. Leave me alone.
你多大了呢? 12岁吗? 你呢? 14岁吗?
How old are you? Twelve? And you? Fourteen?
你们为什么要在这儿呢 在战场上闹着玩吗? 回家去
Why are you here? To play at war? Go home.
- 你是谁啊? 你想干什么呢  - 我想要我的儿子...要活着的
Who are you? What do you want? I want my son. Alive.
你应该为你的儿子自豪 他摧毁了两辆坦克
You should be proud. He destroyed two tanks.
今天元首会亲自表彰他
The Furer will decorate him for it, today.
你还年轻 你在哪个前线打过仗呢
You're still young. At which front did you fight?
我还没有这个荣幸
I haven't had the honour yet.
那是你走运 还不用经历屠杀  现在理智点 送孩子们回家去
Count yourself lucky. Send the children home.
我们要坚守这个阵地直到最后一个人
We'll defend this position to the last man.
哪个阵地? 这不是个阵地 这是个陷阱
Which position? This is not a position, it's a trap.
俄国人将从两面夹击过来 到时候你们会无路可走
The Russians will come from two sides and you won't be able to get out.
- 我们会奋起还击  - 用什么还击呢
We'll shoot back. -What with?
用高射炮
With the anti-aircraft guns.
俄国人有更多的军队正在逼近 他们还有坦克 大炮
The Russians will arrive with several armies, tanks and heavy artillery.
你们到时只能坚持五分钟
Do you really think you'll last even five minutes?
我们向元首宣过誓的
We promised the Furer.
你们还不明白吗? 战争失败了 已经要结束了
Don't you understand? The war is lost.
懦夫
Coward.
快走 马上
Go away. Right now.
如果俄国人来的时候还呆在这儿 你们都会死的
If you're still here when the Russians arrive, you'll all be dead.
第九集团军必须撤退 否则他们会被包围歼灭的...
The 9th army had to retreat or they would have been decimated...
第九集团军不能撤 布塞必须坚持战斗
We won't retreat the 9th army. Busse must fight where he stands.
元首 我们会失去第九集团军的
Furer, then the 9th army is lost.
我们要全力以赴 严阵以待
We'll push back the Soviet armies in the north and east...
... 击退正在北部和东部进攻的苏联军队
...with a ruthless, mighty attack.
用哪支部队呢
Using which units?
斯坦纳从北部进攻然后与第九集团军会师
Steiner will attack from the north and join the 9th army.
第九集团军无法向北移动
The 9th army is unable to move.
敌人的数量十倍于我们
The enemy outnumbers us ten times.
温克的第十二集团军必须支援他们
Wenck's 12th army must support them.
- 第十二集团军已经向易北河西进了  - 那让他转回来
The 12th army is approaching the Elbe. -Then it must turn around.
- 那么西线就会失守  - 你怀疑我的命令吗?
Then the western front would be open. -Do you doubt my orders?
我想我已经说得很清楚了
I think I've been clear enough.
盟军迟早会看到 只有我们才能阻止布尔什维克  我们是抵御这些亚洲军队的最后堡垒
The Allies will see that only we can stop the Bolsheviks.
我们必须保住柏林 只要少数几天 然后我们要和美国人谈判
We have to keep Berlin and make a deal with the Americans.
- 蒙克 你在啊  - 元首
Mohnke, you're here. -Mein Furer.
今天 "克劳塞维茨"战略开始了 柏林将会成为前线城市
Today, 'Clausewitz' started. Berlin will be a front city.
你将成为大本营近周防御指挥官
You will be the commander of the defensive circle around the citadel.
柏林如果开战的化 我们将会战斗到最后一个人
We'll fight until the last man, in Berlin.
但是这儿还有三百万平民 他们必须撤退
There are still three million civilians here. They have to be evacuated.
我知道你担心什么 蒙克 我们一定要冷若坚冰
I understand your concern, Mohnke. But we have to be cold as ice.
我们不能浪费任何精力 在这些所谓的平民身上
We can't spend any energy on so-called civilians.
出于应有的考虑 妇女和儿童怎么办...
With all due respect, what will happen to the women and children...
... 成千上万的伤员和老人怎么办
...and the thousands of wounded and elderly?
在这样的一场战争中 没有什么平民
In a war such as this one, there are no civilians.
元首完全丧失了理智
The Furer has lost all sense of reality.
他在纸上谈兵 他要调动的军队已经不存在了
He's moving divisions around that no longer exist.
斯坦纳的军队已经军心涣散 连自身都难保  现在要斯坦纳发动进攻 太荒唐了
Gruppe Steiner has been scattered, yet Steiner must attack. Madness.
- 但你为什么不告诉他呢  - 他不听人劝
But why don't you tell him that? -He doesn't listen to reason.
- 得想个办法  - 你疯了吗? 他会把我们抛出去的...  - 那又怎样?
Something has to happen. -Are you crazy? He'll throw us out.
我们是军人 我们发誓过为元首效忠的
We're soldiers. We took an oath.
那就要我们不去思考了吗?
Does that mean we can't use our own brains anymore?
这话是你说的吗? 机会主义者 只顾往上爬
And that's coming from you? A ruthless careerist?
你说什么呢
I beg your pardon?
- 你去哪儿了  - 不关你的事
Where were you? -None of your business.
元首 柏林希特勒青年军最成功的坦克射手在此集合
The most successful tank hunters of the Berlin Hitler-Jugend stand before you.
我为你们自豪
I'm proud of you.
这个小伙子用反坦克炮弹摧毁了两辆俄国坦克
This boy took out two tanks using anti-tank shells.
- 他叫彼得·克兰茨  - 那么你就是彼得了
His name is Peter Kranz. -So you're Peter.
我希望我的将军能有你的勇气
I wish my generals were as brave as you.
非常好
Very good.
你们创造了历史
You've made history.
当赫马尼亚从废墟上再次崛起的时候...
And when Germania will rise from these ruins...
... 你们就是英雄
...you will be the heroes.
致敬 所有的人
Heil, to you.
我不知道你们怎么想 真让我心慌 我宁愿是空袭
I don't know about you, but I prefer air raids.
- 我们现在怎么办?  - 他昨天说 如果我要走 他会理解的
What will happen to us? -I could go if I wanted to.
但是现在人人都离他而去 我们不能都走 不是吗?
But everybody is deserting him. We can't all go, can we?
我也不能走
I can't go either.
我也不知道可以去哪儿
I wouldn't know where to go.
我的父母 事实上所有的朋友都告诫过我
My parents and all my friends warned me.
不要和纳粹搅在一起
Don't get involved with the Nazis.
我该怎么说?  "我又回来了 我犯了个错误 我认识到我的错误了"
What should I say: 'Hello, I made a mistake'?
"事情变糟的时候 我承认自己犯了错误"
'When things went wrong, I admitted my mistake.'
不管如何这样可以活下去
Life will go on.
- 你怎么认为呢 长官先生  - 我们一定要走
What do you think, Herr Oberst? -We have to go.
- 去哪儿呢  - 我不知道
Go where? -I don't know.
哪儿需要我们就去哪里
Wherever they need us.
大家到楼上去 要庆祝一下 我准备了个舞会
Let's go upstairs. We'll party.
来啊
Come on.
来啊, 孩子们
Come, children.
今天应该开开心心的
We should have fun today.
无论敌人到哪儿 他们看见的都是废墟
Wherever the enemy goes, all they find is destruction.
那样等于宣判了德国人民的死刑
That's the death sentence for the German people.
没有电 没有汽油 没有饮用水 没有煤 没有交通
No power, no gas, no drinking water, no coal, no traffic.
所有轨道交通 运河 船坞 船闸 船只 火车...  如果毁了一切 我们将回到中世纪
If you destroy everything, our country will go back to the Middle Ages.
这命令让大众生机渺茫
This order denies the people any chance of survival.
如果战争失败了 再失去了人民又怎样
If the war is lost, what does it matter that the people are lost too?
此刻德国人民的生活所需不应该再考虑
The primary necessities of life of the German people aren't relevant, right now.
我们最好自己销毁它们
On the contrary. We'd best destroy them ourselves.
我们的人民这么懦弱...
Our people turned out weak...
... 根据自然法则 他们应该灭亡
...and according to the laws of nature, they should die out.
他们是你的人民 你是他们的元首
They're your people. You're their Furer.
战争结束后剩下的...
What remains after this battle...
... 将只有劣等人群 因为优等人群已经灭亡
...is only the inferior. The superior will have fallen.
来啊, 你们一定要跳的
Come along. You have to dance.
- 可以跳一曲吗? 夫人  - 当然乐意
Care to dance, Frulein Braun? -I'd love to.
- 打扰下  - 没关系
May I? -Go ahead.
怎么了
What's wrong?
我们一定得离开柏林 爱娃 你一定要说服他
We have to leave Berlin, Eva. You must convince him.
或者 你和我一起走
Or else, come with me.
爱娃
你会死的
You'll die.
有人可以现场演奏吗? 我要跳舞
Can somebody play some music? I want to dance.
跳舞
Dance.
- 有什么要求吗?  - 摇摆舞曲
Do you have a request? -As long as it swings.
特劳德尔
Traudl.
这不是真的
It's all so unreal.
像一个你想要醒来却无法摆脱的梦
It's like a dream you can't get out of.
一直持续下去
It keeps on going.
格尔达 我感觉很难受
Gerda, I don't feel well.
特劳德尔 来
Traudl, come.
我没有移动...
I did not move...
我没有移动战地指挥所
I did not move my command post.
向西吗? 怎么会呢
To the west? How so?
- 我离敌人只有1公里  - 进来了 全力掩护!  - 将军
I'm at 1000 meters from the enemy. -General.
医生! 医生在哪里?
喂? 喂?
怎么了 将军
And, general?
- 我要被处死了  - 什么? 为什么呢
I'll be executed. -What? Why?
他们认为我把西南的战地指挥所  撤退到了西部的道伯里茨
They think I moved my command post to the west.
- 理智点 将军  - 跟我来
Be sensible, general. -Come along.
- 申克  - 蒙克
Schenck. -Mohnke.
我在佛斯大街的新帝国首相官邸的公事里  元首现在认命我为大本营的指挥官
I'm under the chancellery. I'm commander of the citadel now.
- 我需要你的帮助  - 太困难了 除了我的副官和我
I need help. -That will be difficult. Everything's gone.
其他人全都撤走了
My assistant and I are the only ones here.
- 你是个医生 是吗?  - 是的 内科医生
You're a doctor, aren't you? -Yes, an internist.
找辆车把你所能找到的药品和绷带...
Commandeer a car and bring all the medication...
... 全都带过来 给我
...you can find, to me.
- 我会尽力的  - 谢谢 快点儿
I'll do my best. -Thanks. Hurry.
我一定要见元首
I need to talk to the Furer.
- 为了什么事  - 我要被处死了
What about? -I'm going to be executed.
在这儿等一下
Wait here.
请交出武器
Your weapon, please.
这儿不行
Not here.
二号岗 明白
Guard post 2. Understood.
将军...
General...
你不能进去
Not you.
- 嗨! 希特勒!  - 嗨! 希特勒!
这儿到底怎么了 为什么我要被处死呢?
What's going on here? Why am I going to be executed?
向西撤退是绝对不允许的 这是元首的命令
You know that any evasive manoeuvre towards the west is forbidden.
不坚决服从本命令的军官都要被逮捕和当场处死
Officers who don't obey, must be executed.
你说什么呢 多日来我的部队一直在进行最严酷的战斗
What do you mean? My troops have been fighting for days.
我的战地指挥部离前线只有一公里
My command post is a kilometre away from the front line.
继续
Continue.
看到这个了吗? 不要用那样的口气对我说话
Do you see this? I don't want you to use that tone with me.
现在 做任何你认为该做的事吧
And now, do whatever you feel you must.
最好你亲自和元首本人谈谈 来吧
It's best if you tell this to the Furer yourself. Come along.
- 你不能过去 长官  - 作战司令部司令蒙克让我来的
You can't pass, Oberst. -Orders from brigade furer Mohnke:
我必须到医院去 我们需要绷带和药物
I have to get into the hospital. We need medication.
医院里面没有人了 他们都走了
There's nobody left. They all took off.
- 伤员呢  - 我怎么知道呢
And the wounded? -How should I know?
我要进去看看 你呆在这儿
I'm going to have a look. You stay here.
千万小心 这里到处都是俄国人
Be very careful. There are lots of Russians here.
看到那儿了吗?  那儿就是德国的边界 那后边就是俄国人的地盘了
See that? That's where the Reich ends. Behind it, is Russkie land.
我可以吗?
May I?
混蛋 混蛋 他为什么不让我去呢
He's damned stubborn. Why doesn't he let me do that?
有人吗?
我早应该回去了 你肯定元首要见我吗?
I should have been back by now. Are you sure the Furer still needs me?
- 喝光  - 元首的命令
Drink. -Furer's orders.
你给元首留下了深刻的印象
You made a big impression on the Furer.
但是你认为斯坦纳不会发动进攻 是吗?
But you don't think Steiner will attack, do you?
我怀疑斯坦纳还能做些什么...
I doubt whether Steiner is able to do anything...
... 但是这一点也许你们比我更清楚
...but you probably know that better than I do.
如果斯坦纳不进攻 柏林就完了
If Steiner doesn't attack, Berlin is lost.
你的报告给元首留下了深刻的印象
The Furer was impressed with your report.
他让你负责柏林的防御
He puts you in command of the defence of Berlin.
我宁愿他把我处死
I'd have preferred it if he executed me.
等他们靠得更近些
Let them get closer.
坦克警报
Tank alert.
别着急 别着急 孩子 他们离得太远
Take it easy. Wait, kid. They're still too far.
一号岗 进去吧 女士们
- 我听到的是德国的大炮吗?  - 恐怕不是
Is it German artillery that I hear? -I'm afraid not.
但斯坦纳不是要开始进攻吗?
But hasn't Steiner's attack started?
你们最好早点离开 时间不多了
You have to go as fast as you can. Time is running out.
但是元首非常有信心可以控制局面 他很肯定
But the Furer has the situation under control.
斯坦纳会使形势逆转
Steiner will make all the difference.
他多次讲 这次进攻将影响整个战争史
He says it will change military history.
元首身边的每个人都知道那是幻想
Everybody, but the Furer, knows that's a fantasy.
- 谁知道他自己是不是相信  - 他为什么要耍我们呢
I even wonder if he believes it himself. -Why would he be playing games?
他还有什么可失去的呢
What does he have to lose?
我一点儿也不相信
I don't believe a word of it.
敌人可能会突破防线
The enemy made a breakthrough.
在南边 他们占领了佐森正朝斯坦斯多夫扑来
They took Zossen and are advancing towards Stahnsdorf.
他们在柏林北郊的弗勒瑙区和潘科区之间活动
They're at the northern city border, between Frohnau and Pankow.
在东部, 他们已到达利希滕贝格  马尔斯多夫 卡尔斯霍尔斯特一带
In the east, they reached Lichtenberg, Mahlsdorf and Karlshorst.
如果斯坦纳进攻 一切都会好起来的
If Steiner attacks, everything will be alright.
元首...
Mein Furer...
斯坦纳...
Steiner...
斯坦纳没有足够的兵力
Steiner didn't have enough force.
没有发动进攻
The attack didn't take place.
凯特尔 约德尔 克莱普斯和布尔格多夫留下来
The following stay here: Keitel, Jodl, Krebs and Burgdorf.
那是个命令 斯坦纳的进攻是个命令
That was an order. Steiner's attack was an order.
你们怎么能无视我的命令呢
How dare you ignore my orders?
事情到了这种地步吗?
Is this what it came to?
所有的部队都在欺骗我 甚至党卫军也是
The military, everybody lied to me. Even the SS.
这些将军们都是些不忠不义的懦夫
The generals are no more than a bunch of disloyal cowards.
我养这样的...
I don't allow that...
- 懦夫 叛徒 饭桶...  - 元首 这有些过分
Cowards, traitors and incompetents. -Furer, this is outrageous.
这些将军是德国人民的渣子
The generals are the scum of the German people.
没有荣誉感
No sense of honour.
称自己是将军不过因为你们在军事学院里呆了几年...
You call yourself general because you spent years at the academy...
... 但你们只学会了怎么用刀叉吃饭
...where you only learnt to use knife and fork.
多少年了 军队只会阻挠我的行动
For years, the military obstructed me.
你们所做的只是在扯我的后腿
All you ever did is thwart me.
我早该把所有的...
I should have had...
... 高级军官都处死 就像斯大林那样
...all the high officers executed. Like Stalin did.
我从来没有进过学院
I never went to the academy.
但我一个人征服了整个欧洲
But I conquered all of Europe on my own.
叛徒
Traitors.
从一开始就对我欺骗和背叛
I've been betrayed and deceived from the start.
对德国人民的不可饶恕的背叛
Such enormous betrayal of the German people.
但所有的叛徒都要偿还 用他们自己的血
But all these traitors will pay. With their own blood.
他们将溺死在自己的血液里
They will drown in their own blood.
冷静 格尔达
Calm, Gerda.
所有的命令都被当成了耳旁风
All my orders have been ignored.
在这样的环境中要我怎么去领导呢
How can I be a leader under these circumstances?
结束了
It's over.
战争失败了
The war is lost.
但如果你们认为这意味着我会离开柏林...
But if you think this means I'll leave Berlin...
... 那么你们错了 我宁愿死在自己的子弹下
...you're wrong. I'd rather shoot a bullet through my head.
想干什么就干什么去吧
Do what you want.
元首不是真的要自杀 是吗?
The Furer wasn't serious about killing himself, was he?
琼格夫人 克里斯蒂安夫人
Frau Junge, Frau Christian.
换好衣服 一小时之内 有架飞机带你们去南部
Get changed. In one hour, a plane will take you south.
一切都没了
Everything is lost.
彻底没了
Completely lost.
你知道我会和你在一起的 你不能把我送走
You know I'll stay with you. You can't send me away.
我也要留下来 元首
I'm staying too, mein Furer.
现在怎么办呢
Now what?
- 不用掩饰什么了  - 这是什么意思?
Time to end this charade.
你要我们停止抵抗吗? 真不可思议
Do you want us to stop fighting? That's inconceivable.
元首一直说 我们不能投降  1918年11月的一幕不能重演 决不
The Furer doesn't want us to capitulate. No more November 1918. Ever.
但他不想负责下去了  他说 "想干什么就干什么去吧"
But he doesn't want to be in charge anymore. He said: 'Do what you want'.
但没有人可以替代他 元首就是元首
Nobody can replace him. He's the Furer.
元首一时糊涂了 他会清醒过来的
The Furer's confused. He'll recover.
很好 但是如果他清醒了 我们下一步能怎么办?
Great. And then what?
我们不能投降 那绝对不是元首的意志
No capitulation. That was never his intention.
- 我们应服从他的意志  - 全是空话
We owe it to him. -Hollow phrases.
我们现在必须采取行动 否则就会来不及的
We have to act now. Or it will be too late.
- 你只想着保住你的脑袋  - 说话注意点
You're only looking after yourself. -Mind your words.
该死
Damn.
我们永远不可能活着从这儿出去 一切全完了
We'll never get out of here alive. It's all over.
我们必须等待
We've got to wait.
连元首自己都没信心了 他要是自杀了 我们怎么办
Even the Furer doesn't believe in it anymore. What will happen to us?
晋瑟说有个通道穿过俄国边境
Gusche says there's a tunnel that goes under the Russian lines.
刚刚你为什么说要和他呆在一起呢
Why did you say you wanted to stay with him?
我不知道 真的
I don't know. Honestly.
炮击停止了 我们出去散散步
It stopped. Let's go for a walk.
特劳德尔
Traudl.
看这儿
Look here.
啊, 我又想再抽烟了
I'm lighting another one.
我们再下去吧
Let's go down again.
送弹药到前面去
医生! 医生在哪里?
冲锋枪失灵了! 联络员! 联络员
- 他们是从哪儿来的呢  - 人民冲锋队 下午才被征召过来的  「人民冲锋队:大战后期德国的地方武装组织」
Where do they come from? -Volkssturm. Drafted this afternoon.
他们必须离开交战区
They have to get out of the field of fire.
人民冲锋队归戈培尔博士直接领导
The Volkssturm is under the direct command of Dr. Goebbels.
我要他们离开这儿 这样太愚蠢了
I want them to go away from there. This is insane.
我要负起责任
I'll take the responsibility.
- 教授 我不知道我们这么做对不对  - 很好
I think this is wrong. -Great.
停车 关掉车灯
Stop. Lights out.
站住, 站在那儿不要动
Stop. Stay where you are.
- 站在那儿不要动  - 还好 是德国人
Stay where you are. -Alright, Germans.
- 救命 他们要杀了我们  - 这都是怎么了
Help. They want to kill us. -What is all this?
- 特别行动  - 开什么玩笑
A Greifkommando. -You're kidding.
- 布尔什维克!  - 住手 放他们走
Stop it. Let those men go.
- 这是怎么回事  - 这里不归你管
What's this? You have no authority here.
他们要逃走 叛徒应该被干掉的
These men are on the run. Traitors will be killed.
他们是些老人 是平民 你不能这样做
They're old men. Civilians. You can't do this.
谁要阻止我? 你吗?
Who's going to stop me? You maybe?
住手 够了
Stop it. That's enough.
解散
Dismissed.
我受不了了 杀了我吧
他是医生
This man's a doctor.
- 你会做手术吗?  - 不会
Can you operate? -Not really.
注意!
和伊塞小姐说 "不要太多的玩具 一个孩子一个就够了"
Don't let the children take too many toys.
也不用太多的睡衣 用不上了 一会儿见
And not too much nightwear. That's no longer needed.
- 部长先生...  - 琼格夫人 我的夫人和孩子很快就到了
Herr Minister... -Frau Junge, my family will arrive soon.
你接待他们一下好吗? 谢谢你了
Can you look after them for a moment? Thank you.
旅长 我能为您做些什么呢
Brigade furer, what can I do for you?
你那些人民冲锋队的人成了俄国人射击的靶子
Your Volkssturm is an easy prey for the Russians.
他们既没有战斗经验也没有合适的武器
They have neither combat experience nor good weapons.
他们对最终胜利的坚定信念 可以弥补这一点
Their unconditional belief in the final victory makes up for that.
部长先生 您如果不能给这些人配备武器 他们就无法战斗
Herr Minister, without weapons these men can't fight.
他们毫无意义地在送死
Their deaths will be pointless.
我不同情他们
I don't pity them.
再说一遍 "我不同情他们"
I repeat: I don't pity them.
这是他们自己选择的命运
The people called this upon themselves.
对有些人来说也许很吃惊 不要再自欺欺人了
This may come as a surprise to you. Don't fool yourself.
我们没有强迫德国人民 是他们给我们的权力
We didn't force the people. They gave us a mandate.
现在他们要为此付出代价
And now they're paying for it.
爱娃 你必须离开元首
Eva, you have to leave the Furer.
不要傻了 这是事关生死的大事
Don't be stupid. This is about life and death.
你怎么能那样说呢 你在哪儿
How can you say that? Where are you?
我不想死在柏林
I decided not to die in Berlin.
- 赫尔曼 我妹妹知道你在哪儿吗?  - 考虑一下吧 我会再打电话回来的
Does my sister know where you are? -Think about it. I'll call you back.
孩子们 你们的房间在右边
Children, your room is to the right.
等我
Wait for me.
- 你好 戈培尔夫人  - 很高兴看到你 琼格夫人
Hello, Frau Goebbels. -Good to see you, Frau Junge.
列队 孩子们
Line up, children.
赫尔嘉 过来 列队
Helga, come. Line up.
- 我们收拾一下 等会儿就可以向希特勒叔叔问好了  - 好呀!
Let's make ourselves look good and then we go say hello to uncle Hitler.
- 你们还记得那首歌吗?  - 记得
Do you remember the song?
没有什么地方的美景
胜得过我辽阔的家园
夜晚在菩提树下
我们自在悠闲
最安全最好的就是从嘴里射死自己
The best thing to do is to shoot yourself in the mouth.
- 然后脑袋就开了花  - 咦!
什么也感觉不到 立刻就会死去
You won't feel a thing. You'll be dead right away.
我要尸体漂漂亮亮的 我可以服毒
I want to be a beautiful corpse. I'll take poison.
如果我准备好英勇地死去 就要没有痛苦
If I have to die, at least without any pain.
这样绝对没有痛苦
That's definitely painless.
死的时候 神经系统和呼吸系统瘫痪
It paralyses the nervous system and the respiratory system.
几秒钟的事
A matter of seconds.
- 可以给我一支吗?  - 我也要
Can I have one too? -Me too.
幸亏希姆莱给了我好几支
Himmler provided me well.
谢谢你
Thank you.
真遗憾 我不能给你更好的礼物
I would have liked to give you a nicer present.
柏林 1945年4月23日
Berlin, 23 April 1945.
亲爱的妹妹 很抱歉给你写这封信
Dear sister. I'm sorry to write you this.
但没有办法 我们每日每刻都可能会离去
But this is how it is. It could be over any moment.
首先 赫尔曼没有和我们在一起
First of all: Hermann isn't with us.
但是我确信你会再见到他的
But I'm sure you'll see him again.
他会渡过难关 在巴伐利亚继续战斗一段时间
He'll get through this and he'll fight from Bavaria.
元首对好的结果不报任何希望
The Furer lost all hope of a good outcome.
亲爱的儿子 不知道你能不能收到这封信
Dear son. I don't know if you'll receive this letter.
也许会有人成全我对你的最后的问候
Maybe someone will allow me to send you a last greeting.
我没有听爸爸的话 留在了他身边
I stayed with daddy against his will.
上周日 元首要帮助我们逃离柏林
Last Sunday, the Furer wanted to help me escape.
但你了解你的妈妈 我们流着同样的血
But you know your mother. We have the same blood.
我想都没有去想 我们的理想破灭了...
I won't even think about it. Our ideology's going down the drain...
... 随之而去的还有一切 使生活美好以及有价值的东西
...and with it, everything that made life beautiful and worthwhile.
没了元首和国家社会主义 我们的生活就没有了意义
After the Furer and National Socialism, there's nothing left to live for.
这也是我把孩子们也带来的原因
That's why I brought the children too.
等待着他们的生活太可怕了
They're too good for the life that awaits them.
如果我亲自为他们救赎 仁慈的上帝会理解我的
God will have mercy on me if I bring them redemption myself.
我要戴着绿宝石手镯直到最后一刻
I'll wear my bracelet with the green stone until the very end.
那以后 我希望你一直戴着它 就象我一直戴着它一样
After that, I want you to always wear it.
不幸的是 我的钻石表还在钟表匠那里
Unfortunately, my diamond watch is with the watchmaker.
我把地址写在了后面 但愿你能幸运地找到它
I included the address below. I hope you're lucky enough to get it.
它应该属于你
I want you to get it.
那个宝石手镯和黄宝石挂件也归你了
You'll also get the bracelet with the topaz pendant.
那是元首在我上一次生日时送给我的礼物
A birthday present from the Furer.
我欠了海泽公司一些钱
I owe some money to the Heise company.
也许还有其它欠债 但不超过1500马克
There may be more debts, but no more than 1500 Reichsmarks.
无论如何 所有给元首的公私信件都要烧掉
All correspondence with the Furer must be burnt.
随信给你寄了些食物和香烟过去  把咖啡分给林德纳和卡特尔一些
I'm sending you some food and tobacco. The coffee is also for Lindner and Kathl.
香烟是给曼蒂的 烟草是给爸爸的 巧克力是给妈妈的
The cigarettes are for Mandi, the tobacco for daddy, the chocolate for mummy.
我不知道还有别的什么事了 今天就到这里吧
I can't think of anything else. That's it for today.
亲爱的妹妹 我希望你天天快乐
Dear sister, I wish you lots of happiness.
记住, 你一定会再见到赫尔曼的
And remember, you will see Hermann again.
最温暖的问候 吻你...
The warmest regards and a kiss from...
... 姐姐
...your sister.
英格
Inge.
听着 凯特尔 我要你今晚就走
Listen, Keitel. I want you to leave this evening.
到道伯里茨那儿去 帮他组织力量
Go to Duitz and help him with the organisation.
我们必须再次开始
Things have to be started up again.
我不明白
I don't understand you.
我们没有油田了 真是场灾难
We have no more oil fields. That's catastrophic.
这使得任何大的举措都无法实施
It makes any serious operation impossible.
这儿的一切解决以后 我们必须把油田夺回来
When everything has been solved here, we must get the oil fields back.
- 还有什么问题吗?  - 没了 元首
Any questions? -No, mein Furer.
很好 一路顺风
Good. Have a good trip.
妈妈!
弗里茨!
弗里茨
弗里茨 不要...
弗里茨!
玛格达!
玛丽亚!
致 元首和帝国首相
嗨 希特勒 戈林
元首 您是否同意 我按照您的决定
Min Fuer, efter som du har besluttet at blive i Berlin...
留在柏林要塞 代表您...
...do you agree that I take charge...
立刻接管帝国的全权指挥 对内对外拥有全权决定权
...with complete freedom of action?
如果22小时以内没有答复...
If I receive no reply by 22 hours...
... 我就假定你已经不能胜任了
...I'll assume you have been incapacitated.
那样我将代表祖国和人民行事了
I will then act on behalf of the country and the motherland.
这是叛国罪 也是对您的背叛
That's high treason. And betrayal of you.
戈林的担心并非完全没有道理
Goering's concerns are not entirely unjustified.
如果我们的通信系统中断了 这种情况随时可能发生
If our communication system fails...
... 我们将和外界失去联系
...we'll be cut off from the outside world.
我们就再也不能发号施令了
We won't be able to issue orders anymore.
我不这么看 我认为戈林想夺权
I think Goering wants to seize the power.
我从来不信任他在上萨尔茨山的党羽
I never trusted his clique on the Obersalzberg.
看起来像一场政变
This looks like a coup.
这个言而无信的小人 这个寄生虫
The loser, the sponger.
暴发户 蛀虫
A parvenu, a lazy bastard.
他怎么能说我不再能控制大局了呢
How dare he say I'm incapacitated?
- 你好 琼格夫人  - 施佩尔先生
Hello.
你们怎么到柏林来的呢
-How did you get into Berlin?
不太容易 但我必须再见元首一面
It wasn't easy, but I must speak to the Furer.
如果我是你 我宁愿先等一会儿
If I were you, I'd wait a bit.
他把空军弄成什么样了?
The Luftwaffe. What did he turn that into?
光凭这一点 就该毙了他
For that alone, he should be executed.
这个抽大麻的毁了整个国家
This morphine addict corrupted the country.
现在又要背叛我个人
And now this.He's betraying me.
还有人民
Me of all people.
我要立刻剥夺戈林的权力
I want Goering stripped of his power, right away.
为了防止我活不到战后...
And, in case I don't survive the war...
... 他应该马上被处死
...he must be executed immediately.
我们会怎么样 还有希望吗?
What's going to happen to us? Is there any hope left?
琼格夫人 你必须离开这儿 否则就太晚了
Frau Junge, leave from here before it's too late.
元首想留下来 我们不能留下他一个人 是吗?
The Furer wants to stay. We can't leave him behind, can we?
他不需要任何人陪他 至少不是你
He doesn't need anybody for what awaits him. And least of all you.
但是戈培尔先生和他的妻子还留在这儿 还有孩子们
But Herr Goebbels and his wife stay here. And the children.
但是那些孩子们...
But the children...
我一直相信...
I have always believed...
我一直相信 会有办法的 不管怎样
...that there was a way out.
进来
Come in.
艾尔伯特 你好
Albert. Hello.
你发烧了
You have a fever.
艾尔伯特 我的心脏再也无法承受了
Albert, I can't stand it anymore.
为什么你不和孩子们一起离开呢 玛格达
Why don't you leave with the children, Magda?
离开 去哪儿呢
Leave? And go where?
我可以给你们安排一艘去施瓦伦岛的游艇
I can arrange for you to be taken to Schwanenwerder by barge.
改装后你们可以藏身其中 直到一切都结束的时候
You can hide until everything's over.
不管怎样 不会太久的
It won't be long now anyway.
我全都考虑过了
I thought about it.
我的孩子们不能在一个没有国家社会主义的世界里成长
My children cannot grow up in a world without National Socialism.
再考虑一下吧 玛格达 孩子们有权利拥有未来
Think about it. The children have a right to a future.
如果国家社会主义灭亡了 也就没有未来了
If National Socialism dies, there will be no future.
我不相信你真的希望那样
I can't believe you really want that.
走吧
Go now.
进来
Come in.
我就知道你会来
I knew you'd come.
你不会丢下元首的
You wouldn't desert the Furer.
我是来向元首道别的 今晚我就回到汉堡去
I've come to say goodbye to the Furer. I'm going back to Hamburg tonight.
当然 你必须去 坐
Of course, you must go. Sit down.
我把你为我设计的一些家具带来了
I took some furniture you designed.
我舍不得把它们丢了
I couldn't leave it behind.
来吃点吧 你一定一天没有吃饭了
Please, you must not have eaten all day.
是这样的
That's true.
你能来真的很重要 这表明你站在他这一边
It's very important that you came. It shows him you're on his side.
他怀疑过吗?
Did he ever doubt that?
近来 他常怀疑你也反对他
Lately, he often thought you were against him too.
我一直说你会过来的 果然你来了
I always said you'd come and here you are.
我想 你当时建议他留在柏林 他非常高兴
I think he liked it that you advised him to stay in Berlin.
我也认为这样最好
I also think it's best.
你知道吗?
And, you know...
... 听起来也许有些疯狂
...it may sound strange...
但我在这儿真的很高兴 我一点儿也不害怕
...but I'm really happy here. And I'm not afraid.
进来
- 你来了  - 元首 我...
You came. -Mein Furer, I...
很好
It's good.
坐下来说
Let's sit down.
我给德国和世界制定了宏伟的计划
I had great plans for the Germans and the world.
没有人理解我 甚至与我出生入死的兄弟们
Nobody understood me. Not even my old brothers in arms.
我们有过多好的机会啊! 整个世界都可以是我们的
The opportunities we had. The whole world was ours to grab.
太晚了
Too late.
我唯一可引以为傲的就是我公开反对犹太人...
I can only be proud for openly fighting the Jews...
... 把犹太人清理出了德国人的生存空间
...and for cleansing the Lebensraum from the Jewish poison.
继续下去并不难 瞬间之后...
I don't find it hard to continue. One brief moment...
... 便是永久的和平
...and then eternal peace.
但是请放过平民 元首
But please spare the people, mein Furer.
如果我的人民不能经受这样的考验...
If my people cannot endure this ordeal...
... 我一滴眼泪也不会流的
...I won't shed a tear.
这是他们应得的
They get what they deserve.
这是他们自己写下的命运
They called this fate upon themselves.
几个月以来...
For months...
这事我必须告诉你...
...I have to tell you this...
... 几个月以来我一直 消极对待你的破坏计划
...for months I have sabotaged your orders for destruction.
有书面材料可以证明  我不但无视你的命令 甚至有时候违反你的命令
I not only ignored your orders, but even acted against them.
我不得不告诉你
I had to tell you.
这丝毫不影响我个人对你的忠诚
This never compromised my personal loyalty to you.
这么说你要走了
So you're leaving.
很好
Good.
再见
Goodbye.
祝你一切都好
I wish you all the best.
先生们 现在总算可以好好吃个饱了
Eat well, gentlemen.
彼得
Peter.
没事的 孩子 没事的
It's alright, son.
他发烧了
He has a fever.
是的 但他还活着
Yes, but he's alive.
忠诚和勇气依然存在于这个世界上
Loyalty and courage still exist in this world.
冯·格莱姆和莱奇小姐 我很高兴...
Ritter von Greim and Frulein Reitsch, how good...
你们两个可以没有大碍的来到这儿 至少在某种程度上
...that the both of you arrived more or less unharmed.
请坐
坐
Sit down.
敌人炮火很猛 但我们还是到了加图
We came under heavy fire, but still arrived in Gatow.
但是街道全部封锁了
From there, we couldn't continue.
我们找了架 Fieseler Storch 轻型飞机  直接飞越了俄国人的边界...
We flew in a Fieseler Storch, over the Russian lines...
... 并降落在东西轴线 离这儿不远
...and landed on the East-West axis, close to here.
在降落之前 苏联人朝我们开了火
Before landing, the Soviets had a go at us.
里特·冯·格莱姆将军 我任命你为德国空军的最高统帅
General Von Greim, I appoint you supreme commander of the Luftwaffe.
因此我提升你为元帅
I hereby promote you to General-Feldmarschall.
你肩上的担子很重
A big responsibility rests on your shoulders.
你必须在一无所有的基础上重建德国空军
You have to rebuild the Luftwaffe from scratch.
我们犯了太多的错误 要毫不留情
Many mistakes have been made. Be ruthless.
人生不会原谅弱者
Life doesn't forgive weakness.
所谓的人道主义只是宗教迷信
This so-called humanity is religious drivel.
同情是宗原罪 我总是说 同情弱者是...
Compassion is an eternal sin. To feel compassion for the weak...
... 对自然的背叛
...is a betrayal of nature.
只有铲除了弱者 强者才能取得胜利
The strong can only triumph if the weak are exterminated.
忠于这条法则 我从不同情什么
Being loyal to this law, I've never had compassion.
面对内部其他种族的反对时...
I've always been ruthless when faced with internal...
... 我总是毫不手软 除此之外别无他法
...opposition from other races. And that's the only way.
例如 猿类...
Apes, for instance...
... 会杀掉所有不合群的猿类
...kill all the odd ones.
适用于猿类的法则 一定也适用于人类
And what applies to apes, must definitely apply to humans.
希姆莱在吕贝克向盟军...
Himmler made an offer to surrender...
... 提出投降
...to the allied powers.
通过贝尔纳多特伯爵
Via Count Bernadotte.
从英国电台获得的消息
A message from the English radio.
希姆莱 人民的希姆莱
Himmler. Himmler of all people.
我忠诚者中最忠实的 却是背叛者中最坏的一个
The most loyal of my loyals. That's the worst betrayal.
戈林 他一直都很堕落
Goering, he was corrupt. Always has been.
施佩尔 心不在焉的艺术家 还有其他人 是的...
Speer, an absent-minded artist. All the others: yes.
但是希姆莱? 他疯了吗?
But Himmler? Has he gone insane?
他一定告诉他们说我病了
He must have told them I'm sick.
甚至或许会说我已经死了
Maybe even dead.
让我和里特·冯·格莱姆 以及莱奇小姐单独呆一会儿
- 叫费格莱因来  - 我们找不到他
And get Fegelein. -We don't know where he is.
什么? 他是希姆莱的副官应该随时待命的
What? He's Himmler's assistant. He must be available.
- 我们已经好几天没见到他了  - 立刻写份报告给我
We haven't seen him for days. -I want a report immediately.
你留下 博士
Please stay here, Doctor.
你和格莱姆立刻飞到多尼茨那里
You and Greim must go as quickly as possible. Fly to Duitz.
他应想尽一切办法 让希姆莱得到应有的惩罚
Tell him to do anything it takes to punish Himmler.
元首 里特·冯·格莱姆和我决定陪你一起殉国
We've decided to die with you.
谢谢你们的忠诚
Thank you for this proof of loyalty.
但希姆莱必须死 他犯了叛国罪
But Himmler must die. He committed treason.
对 我没有让他参与我的计划是正确的
He's no longer privvy to my plans.
元首
Mein Furer?
你认为我会坐等那些犹太猪来我杀?
Do you think I'll sit and wait until those Jewish swine slaughter me?
这只是整个计谋的一部分 我要诱敌深入...
This is part of a huge decoy operation. I've allowed the enemy...
... 他们还以为已经胜券在握了 但是等着瞧 格莱姆
...to invade the Reich and they think they've won.
他们到时会从恶梦中醒来
But mark my words: they have another thing coming.
多尼茨正在北方动员部队 凯塞林在南方
Duitz is mobilising in the north. Kesselring in the south.
我们将包围敌人 将他们粉碎
We'll surround the enemy and crush them.
同时在布拉格待命的三个军将从背后夹击俄国人
From Prague, three armies will attack the Russians, simultaneously, from the back.
元首 我不知道我们还有那么多预备队
I didn't know we still had so many reserve troops.
我可保证不久你就会拥有一千架最先进化的...
I made sure you'll soon have a 1000 of the most modern...
... 喷气飞机
...jets at your disposal.
这样德国空军就又可以重整旗鼓了
With those, you can make the Luftwaffe ready for battle again.
您的天才真是让人不得不顶礼膜拜 而且是在祖国的圣坛前
I kneel to your genius, at the altar of the motherland.
嗨 元首
Heil, mein Furer.
你要求离开柏林?
You also request to leave Berlin?
元首 您知道 党卫军和希姆莱属下的
Mein Furer, as you know, all medical departments...
... 所有医疗部队 都已经离开了柏林
...that fall under the SS and Himmler, have left Berlin.
希姆莱是个叛国者 他逃脱不了惩罚的
Himmler is a traitor. He won't escape punishment.
元首 作为党卫军的帝国医生 我在这里已经无事可做了
Mein Furer, as Reichsarzt SS, I have no more work here.
你想要离开柏林的请求是完全不能接受的
Your request to leave Berlin is unacceptable.
我的家人...
My family...
如果俄国人... 我必须离开
If the Russians... I must leave.
你没做错什么
You did nothing wrong.
后辈们会感谢你所做的医学研究
Future generations will thank you for you medical research.
我会承担全部的责任
I take all the responsibility.
下次再谈吧
We'll talk about it later.
我们找不到团长费格莱因 他没有在工事中
Gruppenfurer Fegelein cannot be found. He's not in the bunker.
什么? 找不到费格莱因?
What, you can't find Fegelein?
那就继续找啊, 我要立刻见到费格莱因
Keep searching. I need to talk to him. Immediately.
如果他没有命令就这样跑掉 那他就是逃兵 是叛徒
If he left just like that, that's desertion. Treason.
叫费格莱因来
Bring me Fegelein.
费格莱因... 费格莱因...
Fegelein. Fegelein.
爸爸 你为什么今天穿着周末才穿的制服?
Daddy, why are you wearing your Sunday uniform?
- 昂斯特 出什么事了吗?  - 没有
Ernst, is something wrong? -No.
谢谢
Thank you.
布丽奇特也饿了
Brigitte is hungry too.
伊瑟 你也该吃点东西
Ilse, you should eat something as well.
- 谢谢  - 不用谢
Thank you. -There you go.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 怎么回事?  - 团长 你被捕了
What is it? -Gruppenfurer, you're under arrest.
- 什么?  - 你有当逃兵的嫌疑
What? -You're suspected of desertion.
- 穿上衣服 跟我们走  - 去你们的
Get dressed. You'll come with us.
搜查这个房间
Search the room.
放开我 你有什么资格命令我
Let go of me. You can't give me orders.
你不会处决赫尔曼的 是吗?
You can't have Hermann executed, can you?
证据确凿 他想逃跑
There's no doubt. He wanted to flee.
那又怎样? 一切都结束了
What does it matter? Everything's over.
想想我可怜的妹妹 她已经怀了赫尔曼的孩子
Think of my poor sister. She's pregnant by Hermann.
他是希姆莱的同伙 他也是叛国者
He collaborated with Himmler. He's a traitor.
对叛国者不能仁慈 不能同情他们
There's no mercy for traitors. No compassion for them.
他将被送上军事法庭然后被处死
He'll be court-martialled and executed.
可现在这又有什么用?
What's the point of that?
这是我的愿望
It is my wish.
你是元首
You're the Furer.
说
Speak.
元首 俄国人越来越近了
The Russians are advancing more and more.
没有武器储备了 空投弹药也不可能
There are no more reserves. Supplies from the air are impossible.
这意味着 不会再有弹药补给了
There is no ammunition coming in anymore.
在北面 俄国人已经离外登丹桥不远了
In the north, the Russians are standing in front of the Weidendammer bridge.
东面到了卢斯特花园 南面到了波茨坦广场
In the east: Lustgarten. South: Potsdammer Platz.
西面到了动物园 离首相府只有三四百米了
West: Tiergarten, about 400 metres away from the chancellery.
- 你们还能坚持多久?  - 最多一到两天
How long can you hold out? -At most, two days.
- 包括政府区吗?  - 是的
Including the government area? -Yes.
作为士兵 我建议突围出柏林的包围
As a soldier, I suggest we flee Berlin. It's surrounded.
您想想 柏林战役让我们损失了  大约一万五千到二万名最好的军官
The battle of Berlin killed about 20,000 of our best officers.
年轻人应该血撒疆场
That's what young people are for.
你的建议是疯狂的 荒谬的
What you suggest is insane. Ridiculous.
想想成千上万的伤员 我们帮不了他们
Think of the thousands of wounded. We can't help them.
元首 命令已经拟好 我保证...
Mein Furer, the orders have been written. I give you my word...
元首不能以不光彩的逃兵形象从世界历史舞台消失
The Furer cannot make a honourless disappearance from world history.
即使突围成功...
Even if an advance is successful...
... 我也只是从一个包围圈进入另一个包围圈
...I'll end up in another troublesome situation.
我将会在旷野或者农场...
I'd have to stay in the open air or on a farm...
... 等待末日来临
...and wait for the end.
温克的第十二军正发动进攻  他可以与布塞的第九军会合...
Wenck is advancing with the 12th army. He can join the 9th...
... 会给俄国人沉重的一击 一切都将迎刃而解
...and give the Russians the final blow.
温克真是好样的 发电报给凯特尔
Wenck's an excellent fellow. Send a telegram to Keitel:
立刻告诉我:  1 温克的先头部队在哪里?
Immediately report to me the following: 1. Where are Wenck's vanguard located?
2 什么时候再次发动进攻?
2. When will they attack again?
3 第九军在哪里?  4 第九军准备在哪里突围?
3. Where is the 9th army? 4. Where will the 9th make a breakthrough?
先生们 你们会看到 我说得对
You'll see, gentlemen. I'll be right.
温克会来的
Wenck will come.
我现在想知道温克是否还有可能发起进攻
I want to know if Wenck can do anything at all.
他那少得可怜的部队是不可能...
It's unlikely that Wenck's small amount of troops...
- 为什么进攻不可能?  - 温克根本不足以抵挡红军的进攻
What's unlikely about the offensive? -Wenck can't do anything anymore.
你刚才为什么不告诉元首? 所有人都疯了吗?
Then why don't you tell the Furer that? Has everybody gone mad?
你以为元首不知道吗? 他决不会投降的
Do you think the Furer doesn't know? He'll never surrender.
我们也不会 我已经经历过一次了 已经够了
And neither will we. I've been through that once. Never again.
跟我来 我得出去
Come along. I have to go.
站住
Stop right there.
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler.
对不起 我睡着了
Excuse me. I fell asleep.
休息得好吗 孩子?
Did you get some rest, my child?
准备好你的速记本
In shorthand.
我的政治遗嘱
My political will.
从我1914年作为一名志愿兵...
More than 30 years have passed...
... 参加一战 为国效力到现在...
...since I made my contribution as a volunteer...
... 已经三十多年了
...during the first World War.
在这三十年我的思考 行动和生活中...
During those 30 years, I learnt to think, act and live...
... 只有对人民的热爱和忠诚让我感动
...out of love and loyalty for my people.
- 对不起 枪声太响了  - 是 是 你坐那里
Excuse me. The shooting. -Please sit down.
时间会流逝...
Centuries will pass...
... 但是在我们的城市和纪念碑的废墟上...
...but from the ruins of our cities and monuments...
... 对那些对我们犯下滔天罪行的人...
...the hatred of the people...
... 的仇恨将时刻不忘
...who did this to us, will continue to flare up.
国际犹太教和它的同盟们
International Judaism and its allies.
怎么了 部长阁下?
What is it, Herr Minister?
你想想看 元首想让我离开柏林
Imagine this. The Furer wants me to leave Berlin.
他下的命令
He ordered it.
我从未违抗过元首的命令
I've never ignored an order from the Furer.
但我这次不会服从 我会留下来陪着元首
But I will ignore this order. I'll stay with the Furer.
求你了 琼格夫人...
Please, Frau Junge...
... 我想向你口述我的遗嘱
...I want to dictate my will to you.
我正在打元首的遗嘱
I'm typing the Furer's will.
很好
Good.
我明白 再说吧
I understand. Some other time.
元首 按照种族法案 我必须问您...
Mein Furer, according to the racial law I'm obliged to ask you:
元首 您是纯正的雅利安人吗?
Mein Furer, are you of Aryan descent?
是的
能让我看您的证件吗?
Can I see your identity card?
- 你在跟元首说话  - 好吧
You're talking to the Furer here. -Alright then.
- 您 布劳恩小姐 您是纯正的雅利安人吗?  - 是的
那就没什么能阻止我们的了
Then there's nothing to stop us.
我现在要问您:您 元首 阿道夫·希特勒...
I'm asking you now: Do you, mein Furer, Adolf Hitler...
- 愿意娶这位爱娃·布劳恩作您的妻子吗? 请回答"愿意"  - 愿意
...take Eva Braun, present here, as your wife? Answer 'yes'.
您 爱娃·布劳恩 愿意嫁给我们的元首...
Do you, Eva Braun, take Furer Adolf Hitler, present here...
- 阿道夫·希特勒吗? 请回答"愿意"  - 愿意
...as your husband? Answer 'yes'.
我宣布你们结为夫妻
Then I declare you man and wife.
来两个人
Two men here.
都会好的
Everything will be alright.
- 你必须赶快去元首那里  - 什么? 这个时候?
You must go to the Furer right away. -Now?
- 还能支持多久?  - 也许20个小时 最多了
How long can we hold out? -Twenty hours, no more.
俄国人从四周已经逼近到几百米了  目前我们迫使他们停了下来
The Russians are close. At the moment, we forced them to stop.
蒙克 西方民主已经没落
You know, Mohnke. The western democracies are decadent.
他们将臣服于东方人
They'll succumb to the people from the east.
很好 谢谢你
All the best. Thank you.
这不仅仅是为了德国
It wasn't just for Germany.
凯特尔来的电报
A message from Keitel.
1 温克的部队被挡在施维劳湖南面
1. Wenck's vanguard are stuck south of Schwielowsee.
2 第十二军无法继续进攻柏林
2. The 12th army can't continue the attack on Berlin.
3 第九军已经被重重包围
3. The 9th army is completely surrounded.
元首 请指示 如果弹药耗尽我们该怎么办?
What do we do when the last ammunition reserves have been exhausted?
我决不投降 决不
I'll never surrender. Never.
我也不允许你和其他的指挥官投降
I forbid you, and the other commanders, to surrender.
听着 晋瑟 我的妻子和我会自杀
Listen, Gusche. My wife and I are going to commit suicide.
我不想我的尸体落到俄国人手上
I don't want my corpse exposed by the Russians.
无论死活 我都不想落在俄国人手上
I don't want them to get me, dead or alive.
我想立即火化 不让任何人找到
I want to be burnt and never to be found.
晋瑟 你保证...
Gusche, I want you to promise me...
... 保证无论如何一定做到
...that you will do all that it takes.
元首...
Mein Furer...
... 这是一项可怕的命令 但我会执行的
...this is a terrible order, but I will execute it.
- 肯普卡  - 埃里希 我需要二百升汽油
Kempka. -Erich, I need 200 litres of petrol.
你疯了吗? 我到哪儿去找这么多汽油?
Are you mad? Where should I find them?
从停着的汽车里
From the parked vehicles.
- 你要这么多汽油干什么?  - 电话里我不能说
What's all that petrol for? -I can't say.
来吧 元首要见我们
Come, please. The Furer wants to see us.
要我告诉元首 你不舒服吗?
Should I tell the Furer you're indisposed?
我的烂肺
It's only my collapsed lung.
反正都是死
I'll die soon anyway.
对不起
Excuse me.
过来 教授先生
Over here, Herr Professor.
请稍等
One moment, please.
对不起
Excuse me.
抱歉打扰了你们重要的工作
I'm sorry to interrupt your important work.
元首 相信最后的胜利
Mein Furer, keep faith in the final victory.
带领我们 我们会跟随您的
Lead us and we shall follow.
来吧
Come along.
- 这里有的是地方!  - 请坐
Join the gang.
过来喝一杯
Come. Have a drink.
- 除了喝酒 没什么好做的了  - 请坐吧
Besides drinking, there's little we can do. -Do sit down.
- 这样很好  - 是的 现在的形势是没什么指望了 可以说是糟糕
That's better. Yes, the situation is pretty shitty.
- 我们能坐下吗?  - 非常荣幸 小姐...
Can we sit down? -Please do, Frulein...
- 夫人...  - 你可以叫我希特勒夫人
Frau... -That's Frau Hitler.
这样也算是名正言顺
It's alright.
可惜我们不能出去了
A pity we can't go outside anymore.
因为您想光荣地死去
Only if you want to die a heroic death.
- 弗里茨 管好你自己  - 遵命 一鼓作气!
Fritz, control yourself a bit. -Yes. Control.
掩护!
Take cover.
没什么!
嗨 希特勒!
- 你在这儿干什么?  - 我有事向元首汇报
What are you doing here? -I have to report to the Furer.
你现在不能进去 坐下
You can't right now. Sit down.
坐下 喝酒
Sit. Drink.
我来介绍一下希特勒夫人
Let me introduce Frau Hitler.
这么年轻 而且有那么多勋章 您一定很自豪
So young and so many decorations. You must be proud.
失陪一下 我不能再喝了
Excuse me. I'm not used to drinking anymore.
你可以用我们的洗手间 是的 去吧
You can use our toilet.
如果你的手发抖 子弹也许只能破坏视觉神经
If your hand shakes, the bullet might only hit an optic nerve.
因此我建议 一定要同时服毒药
That's why it's good to also take the poison.
你咬碎胶囊时 抠动扳机
When you bite through the capsule, pull the trigger.
时间够吗?
Will I have enough time?
一两秒后 毒性才开始发作
The poison starts working after one or two seconds.
托诺 你也过来
Tornow, you too.
过来 布伦蒂
Come Blondi.
琼格夫人 我认识他...
You know, Frau Junge, I've known...
我丈夫 已经15年了
my husband for more than 15 years.
但是仔细想想 尽管他爱说话
But when I think about it, I know nothing about him.
可我一点也不了解他
Even though he likes to talk.
我渴望柏林 但他现在不一样了
I longed for Berlin, but he's so different now.
他现在只和我聊狗和素食了
He only talks about dogs and vegetarian food now.
我常常会讨厌布伦蒂
I hate Blondi.
有时我偷偷在桌子底下踢它  阿道夫就会奇怪 它怎么有点怪怪的
I sometimes kick her and Adolf then wonders why she acts strange.
有时我想他不想让任何人真正了解他
I think he doesn't want anybody to really know him.
... 在他的私生活中 他会很有爱心
...he can be so caring in his private life.
又会说些粗鲁的话
And then he uses that rude language again.
你是说当他是元首的身份的时候?
When he's the Furer, you mean?
来 再抽一支
Come, let's smoke another one.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你有那么多烦心的事情 我还在这里抱怨
You have so many worries and here I am, whining.
琼格夫人 我把这件大衣送你给 作为分手的礼物
Frau Junge, I'm giving you this coat as a goodbye present.
我一直喜欢身边有穿着讲究的女士, 希望你喜欢
I like fashionable ladies. I want you to enjoy it.
我真是受宠若惊 谢谢
What a surprise. Thank you.
我只是不知道什么场合穿
I just don't know where and when I can wear it.
想办法逃出去
Please, try to get out of here.
答应我
Promise me.
谢谢 很好 曼切丽小姐
Thank you. That was very good, Frulein Manziarly.
时间到了 结束了
The time has come. It's finished.
元首想道别 跟我来
The Furer wants to say goodbye. Come with me.
你是帝国最勇敢的母亲
You're the bravest mother of the Reich.
元首 您让我成了全德国最幸福的女人
Furer, you made me the happiest woman in Germany.
替我问候我美丽的巴伐利亚家乡
Salute my beautiful Bavaria.
孩子们 你们在这儿干什么?
Children, what are you doing here?
我们想见爱娃阿姨和希特勒叔叔
We want to see aunt Eva and uncle Hitler.
- 你们吃饭了吗?  - 只吃过早餐
Have you eaten anything yet? -Only breakfast.
别走开 我去找些吃的来 马上就回来
Stay here, I'll get something to eat. I'll be right back.
同志们 这是外面来的最新消息
Comrades, this is the latest news from the outside.
柏林简直是废墟 这里曾是房子 那里也曾是房子
Berlin is full of warehouses: There were houses here, there were houses there.
晋瑟先生 我一定要和元首再说句话
Herr Gusche, I want to speak to the Furer.
我必须说
Please, I have to.
戈培尔夫人 元首已经下了命令 不想受到打扰
Frau Goebbels, the Furer doesn't want to be disturbed.
拜托 晋瑟 就一会儿
Please, Gusche, just for a moment.
求你了
Please.
元首 戈培尔夫人来了
Mein Furer, Frau Goebbels is here.
什么事?
What is it?
元首 我求您 离开柏林吧
Mein Furer, I beg you: Leave Berlin.
别抛下我们 没有您我们会变成什么样?
Don't leave us Furer. What will become of us?
明天我会被众人诅咒 但命运不允许其它的结局
Tomorrow, I'll be cursed by millions, but that's how it is.
起来
Get up. Come.
来吧
Come.
特劳德尔阿姨 我觉得打雷很有意思
Aunt Traudl, I like it when it thunders.
- 为什么?  - 在这里我们没事的
Why? -Nothing can happen to us here.
- 是吗?  - 当然
Can it? -No.
打中了
Gotcha.
帝国领袖先生 结束了
Reichsleiter, it's over.
我宣布:元首死了
The Furer is dead.
爸爸来了
There's daddy.
你是不是疯了? 你要的那些该死的汽油在外面了...
Are you crazy? For that damned petrol of yours...
埃里希 你最好闭嘴
Erich, shut up.
退后
Stand back.
快点 继续吧
Come on, continue.
继续
Continue.
不要! 不要!
不要! 不要! 不要!
No, don't.
放开爷爷
Let grandpa go.
秩序 秩序
Order. Order. We must have order.
这里必须恢复秩序
Order has to return.
跑啊, 爷爷 跑啊
他们两个在那边 马上回来
这边 我们认识废墟中的路 你可以相信我们 快点!
This way. We know the way. You can trust us.
快
Hurry.
"我是站在红色野兽这一边的"
I was on the side of the Red Beasts.
"我拥护布尔什维克"
I supported the Bolsheviks.
希望俄国人收到了我们的电报
Let's hope the Russians got our message.
- 很快就会知道的  - 也许不会
We'll soon find out. -Or not.
有什么消息 将军?
What news do you have, General?
阿道夫·希特勒和他的妻子在地下掩体里自杀了
Adolf Hitler and his wife committed suicide in the bunker.
新政府授权我与你们...
The new government authorised me...
... 进行和平谈判
...to start peace talks...
... 我们两国在战争中蒙受了最大的损失
...between our countries, that both suffered severe losses.
将军 如果你是我 你会和我讲和吗?
General, if you were me, would you make peace with you?
我的政府不会接受无条件投降
My government will never accept unconditional surrender.
根据目前的形势 你没有其他选择
Given the situation, you have no other choice.
投降? 决不 太可耻了
Surrender? Never. That's shameful.
几年前 我从红军手中占领了柏林...
Years ago, I conquered Berlin on the Reds...
... 我将誓死保卫这座城市
...and I'll defend the city to my dying day.
在我仍然生为帝国首相的这几个小时里...
In the short time I have as Chancellor...
... 我是不会签投降协议的
...I'll never sign a surrender treaty.
- 我们必须保护老百姓  - 元首的命令是不可改变的
It's for the sake of the people. -The Furer's orders are final.
太荒唐了 我们必须进行谈判
This is crazy. We have to start negotiations.
我再说一遍 我决不投降
I repeat, gentlemen: I do not surrender.
- 马上发个电报给朱可夫元帅  - 朱可夫元帅?
Send a message to Marshal Zhukov. -Zhukov?
- 怎么回事?  - 这太荒唐了 我们必须把这城市交给俄国人
What's happening? -We're surrendering.
那我先杀了你 元首不允许投降
Then I must kill you. The Furer forbids any surrender.
- 多长时间后发作?  - 大约四个小时
How long does it work? -Around four hours.
有一天 四只小猪惊奇地看到
一匹灰马拉着一辆车驶向森林
而一个人则驾驭着这匹马 他在离他们家不远的地方...
停下来休息 他们警惕地从他们的小窗偷偷张望...
并且把前门关紧了 獾也在家 他就用了一点他的魔法
- 来帮助他们  - 孩子们 医生带来了以前我跟你们说过的药
Children, the doctor has the medication I told you about.
有点苦 但很有效
It's a bit bitter, but it will work.
每人一口
A sip for everybody.
谁第一个来?
Who wants to go first?
海德 你一直都很勇敢
Heide, you're always so brave?
喝得很好 再来一点
Have another sip.
看见没有? 没那么难喝吧
See? That wasn't so bad.
很好 赫尔默特
Well done. Helmut.
孩子们 你们很勇敢  这些药会让你们在潮湿的掩体中不生病
This medication makes sure you don't get ill in this humid bunker.
可是现在掩体里一点也不潮湿啊
But it's not humid in the bunker.
做得好
Well done.
赫尔嘉
Helga.
我不想喝
I don't want to.
- 什么? 你想生病吗?  - 求你了 妈妈 我不想喝
What's that? Do you want to get sick? -Please, mama. I don't want to drink it.
别哭 宝贝 哭是没用的
Don't cry, baby. That doesn't help.
你必须把药喝了
You have to drink the medicine.
来吧! 赫尔嘉
赫尔嘉
Helga.
赫尔嘉! 现在喝吧 喝吧
- 来吧 把嘴张开  - 爸爸
Come on, open your mouth.
快点!
喝啊! 喝啊!
好了 晚安 孩子们
Goodnight, children.
总有一天 谎言会破灭...
One day the lie will fall apart...
... 黑暗之中将燃起希望之火
...and there will be light in the darkness.
请再读一遍给我听
Please read that.
总有一天 谎言会破灭 黑暗之中将燃起希望之火
One day the lie will fall apart and there will be light in the darkness.
我们重新来 总有一天谎言将破灭...
Let's do it differently. One day the lie will collapse...
... 真理将再次获胜
...and truth will triumph once again.
到那时候 我们将屹立于众人之上...
At that moment, we will stand above everybody...
纯正...
...pure and...
完美
immaculate.
- 你会知道 我们根本没有机会  - 那又怎么样? 我想逃出去
We don't stand a chance. -So what? I want to get away.
我们怎么穿过俄国人的防线?
How do we get through the lines?
不管了 我一刻也不想留在这儿了
Doesn't matter. I'm not staying another minute.
- 我们会死的  - 不会那么糟糕的 我肯定
We'll die. -It won't be that bad, surely.
如果我们留下 俄国人肯定会抓住我们
If we stay, the Russians will get us for sure.
祝好运
All the best.
走吧
Come, let's go.
1945年4月30日 元首结束了自己的生命...
On 30 April 1945, the Furer committed suicide...
... 抛下了所有忠于他的人
...and in doing so, he deserted everybody who was loyal to him.
你们忠于元首的德国士兵们...
You, German soldiers, were loyal to the Furer and were prepared...
... 本已准备继续为柏林而战 尽管已经弹尽粮绝
...to continue the battle for Berlin, although ammunition was in short supply...
... 继续抵抗已经毫无意义
...and further resistance was pointless.
因此我宣布立即停火
I hereby declare an immediate cease-fire.
你们每继续抵抗一小时...
Each hour you continue fighting...
... 都会延长柏林人民和我们伤员的痛苦
...prolongs the suffering of the people of Berlin and of our wounded.
经过与苏军统帅的磋商...
In agreement with the supreme command of the Soviet troops...
... 我要求你们立即停止抵抗
...I order you to stop fighting immediately.
威德林 前柏林卫戍区司令
Weidling, former commander of the Berlin defence area.
请给我一杯水
A glass of water, please.
我不再需要你了
I don't need you anymore.
游戏结束了
The game's over.
- 大夫 时间到了 马上天黑了  - 你没看到这儿发生了什么?
It's time. -Don't you see what's going on here?
我需要你做随行医生 我必须坚持这一点
I insist that you help us, as a doctor.
那好吧
Alright, then.
走吧 你已经做了很多了 谢谢
Go. You did a lot. Thank you.
- 谢德勒 快点 跟我们走  - 对不起 我哪儿都不去
Schule, hurry. Come on. -I'm not going anywhere anymore.
继续走
Come along.
- 你没事吧?  - 没事  - 继续走
Are you alright? -Keep going.
攻击手克吕格和他的部队保卫了沃尔夫桥...
Sturmmann Kruer and his group defended the Wolf Bridge...
... 因此被授予二级铁十字勋章
...and he receives the Iron Cross.
攻击手瓦格纳摧毁了两个机枪暗堡  阻止了普特卡默街的袭击...
Sturmmann Wagner took out two machine-gun nests...
... 因此被授予二级铁十字勋章
...and therefore, receives the Iron Cross.
攻击手劳赫穿越敌人防线传递重要情报...
Sturmmann Rauch has gotten messages through the lines...
... 因此被授予二级铁十字勋章
...and receives the Iron Cross.
其他人来了
The others are coming.
哦 天哪
隐蔽 穆勒
Take cover, Muler
- 格尔达  - 拉我出来!
我出不来了! 救命啊!
站住! 是谁?
Who's that?
德国人
A German.
希维尔先生?
Herr Hewel?
希维尔! 感谢上帝 你还活着
Thank God, you're alive.
其他人呢?
Where are the others?
不知道 琼格夫人 也许在某个地方
I don't know, Frau Junge. Somewhere. Maybe.
我这个团大部分人都死了
Most people from my group must be dead.
我不该离开地堡的
I should never have left that bunker.
我早该自杀的 可是我做不到
I should have shot myself, but I couldn't.
先吃点东西吧 想死有的是时间
Eat something first. There's always enough time to die.
你和女人们待在一起
You stay with the women.
来吧
Come along.
- 俄国人已经包围了我们  - 我们会怎么样呢?
The Russians have surrounded us. -What's going to happen to us?
也许你能穿过去 你试试看
Maybe you can get through. You could try.
我不会再挪一步了
I'm not taking another step.
想想看 俄国人追的是我们
Think about it. The Russians are after us.
作为女人 你们也许还有机会 试试看吧
As a woman, you might have a chance. Try it.
祝好运
Good luck.
经过俄国人的时候 不要看他们的眼睛
When you walk past the Russians, don't look them in the eyes.
记住这一点 一切顺利
Remember that well. All the best.
俄国人
The Russians.
- 格尔达 我们走吧  - 你走吧
Gerda, let's go. -You go.
- 我走不动了  - 拜托
I'm exhausted. -Please.
我得试一试 别生我气
I have to give it a try. Don't be angry with me.
我会没事的
I'll be alright.
大夫 大夫
Herr Doktor.
我的伙伴们想投降 我能加入你们吗?
My comrades want to surrender. Can I join you?
元首已经死了 你想打一场自己的战争吗?
The Furer's dead. Do you want to continue the war on your own?
我在恪守自己的誓言
I'm obliged by my oath.
这样 那你最好去找旅长
Then you'd better go to the Brigadefurer.
- 俄国人正在疏散广场  - 怎么样?
The Russians are evacuating the square. -So?
没有抵抗 没有交火
No opposition. No shooting.
他们最多一小时内就会到达这里
Then they'll be here within the hour.
我需要听听你们的意见 我们怎么办?
What shall we do?
- 我们不能无抵抗地投降 那样太没有尊严了  - 你到底什么意思?
We can't surrender. -What exactly do you mean?
我们全部留在这个地方 俄国人到来的时候  我们会打完所有的子弹
When the Russians come, we'll empty our weapons on them.
- 最后一颗子弹是留给我们自己的  - 这样太过火了
The last bullets are for ourselves. -That's radical.
这种冠冕堂皇的谋杀或自杀是否是唯一的可能呢?
Is this prestigious murder and suicide our only option?
我们是党卫军军官 应该追随元首赴黄泉
We're SS officers. We can't survive the Furer.
还有谁是这样想的?
Who agrees with me?
走吧
Let's go.
- 过来跟我一起坐会儿吗?  - 乐意奉陪
Come and sit down with me? -Please.
- 你为什么想活下去?  - 你呢? 你为什么一定要死?
Why do you want to continue living? -And you? Why do you want to die?
看见这个了?
See this?
元首亲自给我的
The Furer gave it to me personally.
- 最后的勋章?  - 也许
As a last decoration? -Maybe.
希特勒道别时留给我的 我向他保证过
A goodbye present from Hitler. I had to promise him something.
他要我保证 如果俄国人抓住了我 我就自杀
If the Russians get me, I have to kill myself.
他要你保证要自杀吗? 可为什么呢?
Did he make you promise that? But why?
也许他不想我被迫...
Maybe he didn't want me to be forced...
... 说他的坏话
...to say anything bad about him.
但是作为外交官 你受国际法保护
But, as a diplomat, you're under international protection.
你不应该坚守自己的承诺 这对谁有好处呢?
Who will benefit if you stick to your deal?
他们来了
There they are.
别开枪 同志
Don't shoot, comrades.
我们投降了 战争结束了
We surrendered. The war is over.
结束了
It's over.
1945年5月7日实行全面投降
Complete surrender took place on 7 May 1945.
5月8日午夜停止抵抗
Hostilities were suspended on 8 May.
至此 战争已夺去了五千万人的生命
The war took the lives of more than 50 million people.
六百万犹太人在德国的集中营被杀害
6 million Jews were killed in German concentration camps.
格尔达·克里斯蒂安成功逃脱 避免了被监禁的命运
Gerda Christian managed to escape and avoid imprisonment.
她在1977年4月14日死于杜塞尔多夫
She died in Duseldorf on 14 April 1997.
申克博士被苏联逮捕 1953年被释放
Dr. Schenck was released in 1953 by the Soviets.
1998年12月21日于亚琛去世
He died in Aachen on 21 December 1998.
威廉·蒙克被苏联逮捕 1955年被苏联释放回国
Wilhelm Mohnke was released by the Soviets in 1955.
他2001年8月6日死于艾肯佛德附近的但普
He died in Damp, near Eckernfude, on 6 August 2001.
赫尔穆特·威德林被苏联逮捕 1955年死在狱中
Helmut Weidling died in captivity, in 1955.
威尔纳·哈泽在医院的防御工事中被红军逮捕
Werner Haase was arrested in the bunker, by the Red Army.
1945年死在苏联战犯监狱
He died in captivity, in 1945.
奥托·晋瑟被苏联逮捕
Otto Gusche was arrested by the Soviets.
1956年从东德鲍岑监狱被释放 2003年死在波恩附近的洛马
He was released in 1956 and died in Lohmar, in 2003.
汉娜·莱奇在战争中幸存 她死于1979年8月28日
Hanna Reitsch survived the war and would break many flying records.
生前多次创造了滑翔和动力飞行的世界纪录
She died on 28 August 1979.
罗伯特·里特·冯·格莱姆  1945年5月24日在萨尔茨堡自杀
Robert Ritter von Greim committed suicide on 24 May 1945.
海因茨·林格和约翰尼斯·亨切尔被苏联逮捕
Linge and Hentschel were arrested by the Soviets.
林格1955年被释放 1980年死于不来梅
Linge was released in 1955 and died in 1980.
亨切尔1949年被释放 1982年4月27日死于亚亨
Hentschel was released in 1949 and died in 1982.
康斯坦泽·曼切丽在柏林的逃亡中失踪
Constanze Manziarly disappeared without a trace, during her flight.
艾尔伯特·施佩尔1945年在弗伦斯堡被捕
Albert Speer was arrested in Flensburg, in 1945.
他在纽伦堡审判中被判二十年监禁
He was sentenced to 20 years, in Nuremberg.
1966年被释放 1981年死于伦敦
He was released in 1966 and died in London, in 1981.
凯特尔和约德尔在纽伦堡审判中被判死刑并被枪决
Keitel and Jodl were sentenced to death in Nuremberg and executed.
赫尔曼·戈林被判死刑
Hermann Goering was sentenced to death.
他临刑前在自己的牢房自杀
He committed suicide in his cell, shortly before his execution.
亨里希·希姆莱试图用假名逃跑
Heinrich Himmler tried to escape using a false name.
被识破后 自杀身亡
After he was found out, he committed suicide.
马丁·伯尔曼和路德维希·斯通普费格  1945年5月2日早晨...
Martin Bormann and Ludwig Stumpfegger committed suicide...
... 在列尔特火车站附近自杀
...on 2 May 1945, near the Lehrter Bahnhof.
罗库斯·米希1955年被苏联释放
Rochus Misch was released by the Soviets in 1955.
现在仍住在柏林
He still lives in Berlin.
特劳德尔·琼格被划分为"年轻的追随者"
Traudl Junge was classified as a 'young follower'.
她先后担任了多家企业的秘书  住在慕尼黑直至2002年去世
She worked as a secretary and lived in Munich, until her death in 2002.
在纽伦堡审判期间 我听到的那些可怕的事情...
All the horror I heard about during the Nuremberg trial...
... 六百万犹太人 持不同政见者 其他种族的人...
...the 6 million Jews, dissidents or people of another race...
... 他们的死深深震动着我
...who died, shocked me deeply.
但我没有将其与我的过去联系起来
But I hadn't made the connection with my own past yet.
我一直安慰自己 作为个人我并没有过错
I reassured myself by thinking I wasn't personally guilty of it.
对此毫不知情 不知道问题如此严重
And that I hadn't known about the sheer size of it.
直到有一天 我经过弗朗兹·约瑟夫大街...
But one day, I walked past a commemorative plaque...
... 为索菲·肖尔而建的纪念碑
...for Sophie Scholl, here in the Franz-Joseph-Strasse.
我看到她跟我差不多年纪...
I saw that she was my age...
... 她在我投靠希特勒的那一年遇害
...and that she was executed in the year I joined Hitler.
直到这时我才明白...
And only then did I realise...
年轻不是借口
that youth is no excuse.
这也许有助于理解事情的真相
And that it might have been possible to find out the truth.